<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="whichsections" xreflabel="Which sections of the book?">
  <?dbhtml filename="which.html"?>


  <title>Which Sections of the Book Do I Want?</title>

  <para>
    GLFS stands as a format in between LFS and BLFS so this
    part is crucial to understanding what you need to read and/or
    follow in order to get out of the system that you desire.
    For starters, LFS is meant to be followed in a linear manner,
    whereas BLFS handles things by putting related packages in
    the sections they are best described as categorically.
    For example, printer software being in a printer section,
    although most packages can be discarded by the user.
  </para>

  <para>
    Not every chapter will be necessary depending on what you
    want. Some packages may also not be necessary.
  </para>

  <para>
    By default, every user should read the multilib chapter as
    most users that want <application>Steam</application> and/or
    <application>Wine</application> should have a x86_64
    CPU capable of 32-bit emulation. If that chapter is skipped,
    you might get a headache later on.
  </para>

  <para>
    The following chapter is Shared Dependencies. Every user
    who wants <application>Steam</application> and/or
    <application>Wine</application> will want to read this chapter
    as both projects use the packages. Most of this chapter is
    necessary. However, it is recommended to check the dependency
    lists of Steam and Wine to see what exactly you need from a
    given section. If you are in doubt, (re)install all of the listed
    packages in that chapter. If you don't use them in this book, it
    still may be useful for some packages in BLFS.
  </para>

  <para>
    The next chapter is Steam, which covers all the packages,
    patches, configuration, and setup necessary to get
    <application>Steam</application> working and capable of the
    playing the following: Linux games, Windows games via Proton,
    and games using OpenGL, Vulkan, and Direct3D. It covers both
    regular compilation of packages and lib32 compilation of some
    of the same packages. If you read the multilib section and
    decided that you desire NOT to go with multilib (despite any
    warnings), you can ignore the lib32 variants of packages.
    Otherwise, follow every step unless told otherwise in the
    respective sections or are presented with options.
  </para>

  <para>
    The following chapter that most users will need is Wine. Likewise
    with the Steam chapter, users should follow every step in this
    chapter if they want to install <application>Wine</application>
    and use it. The Wine chapter at the moment does not consider
    retrofitting and will handle it in a similar manner to Arch: build the
    MinGW-w64 toolchain, install the audio and video components, then finally
    <application>Wine</application> itself.
  </para>

  <para>
    The last chapter covers quality of life improvements and packages.
    This chapter is not required but recommended.
  </para>

  <para>
    We hope you enjoy using GLFS and that it provides you most of your
    gaming needs!
  </para>

</sect1>
